Fasting is put to the test
for a number of diseases.
Does it help?
Watch the video to find out,
and check out the Doctor’s Note below
for other videos on the topic.
"Fasting for Rheumatoid Arthritis
and Autoimmune Disease"
Alan Goldhamer is the founder
of the TrueNorth Health Center
in Santa Rosa, California, which has
fasted 10,000 people for conditions
ranging from diabetes and cardiovascular
disease to autoimmune diseases.
He noted that conditions that
seem to be tied to dietary excess
tend to respond predictably
to the use of fasting
followed by a health-promoting diet,
which he describes as a low salt,
all plant, high fiber, low fat,
low protein, and low sugar diet.
This approach offers people
an option to eliminate the cause
of lifestyle diseases often to
the point where the medication
is no longer needed, in contrast
to conventional medicine,
which is more about the
suppression of the symptoms
associated with the disease, rather
than removing the underlying root cause.
Goldhamer put it this way:
If you treat high blood pressure
or type 2 diabetes or autoimmune
disease medically, they'll tell you,
"You'll be on these medications
the rest of your life."
That’s them in effect promising
you, if you follow their advice
to the letter, “you will be
sick the rest of your life.”
Preliminary data suggests fasting
may benefit metabolic diseases,
pain syndromes, high blood pressure,
chronic inflammatory diseases,
allergic diseases, and
psychosomatic disorders,
but the highest level of evidence
we have for the benefits of fasting
are in regards to rheumatic diseases:
autoimmune inflammatory joint
diseases, like rheumatoid arthritis.
Nearly a century ago it was
written that “diet treatment
is not generally recognized
by the medical profession…
as one of the weapons with
which to attack [such diseases].”
This attitude persisted
until relatively recently,
but a systematic review of
controlled trials has since
“shown a statistically and clinically
significant beneficial long-term effect.”
Rheumatoid arthritis has a
well-known genetic component,
but the concordance rate, the chance
that a pair of identical twins
both get it when one has
it is probably under 30%,
despite having the
same genes, leaving 70%
to be explained by non-genetic factors.
Even if we don't know exactly
what those factors are,
“fasting [has been compared] to
rebooting the hard drive in a computer.
Sometimes, the [drive] gets corrupted
and you don’t know exactly
where the problem is.
But if you just turn
it off and reboot it,…
that corruption
[may get] cleared out.”
The evidence base started with
case reports, fasting followed by
a plant-based diet, remarkable reports
of years of pain and stiffness…
gone within a week, and,
more importantly,
stayed gone on the healthier diet.
One after another like that, but case
reports are just glorified anecdotes.
There have been studies
going back decades suggesting
fasting may represent the most rapid,
available way to induce relief
of arthritic pain and swelling for
patients who have rheumatoid arthritis,
but the studies often failed to
have control for the placebo effect,
which is especially important when
it comes to relying on self-reported
subjective symptoms such as
pain and general well-being.
But there are objective measures,
lab tests of inflammation
that don’t appear to
be affected by placebos,
and that’s what you can
see in controlled trials,
starting immediately and remaining
down for at least a year.
Ten different measures of inflammation
significantly decreased
after the fasting and subsequent
meat- and egg-free diet,
whereas none of the parameters
budged in those disease victims
that continued to eat their regular diets.
And this squelching of inflammation
translated into a significant reduction
in pain, morning stiffness,
loss of grip strength,
and number of tender
and swollen joints.
Even a year after the trial was over,
those who benefited from the diet
continued to benefit in
terms of pain, stiffness,
and tender and swollen joints,
presumably because they stuck with it.
There is little doubt that while
fasting both inflammation and pain
are relieved, but if you go back to
the same diet you were on before,
the inflammation returns—unless,
evidently, the fasting period
is followed by a vegetarian
diet. Why might that be?
It could be due to changes in the
microbiome,
the improvement in symptoms
coincided with a significant alteration
of the intestinal flora,
which may somehow be beneficial,
perhaps by strengthening the gut barrier.
We know fasting can decrease
the leakiness of the gut
in rheumatoid arthritis patients,
but we don’t yet know what role,
if any, this plays in the disease process.
It could be as simple as eicosanoids,
the mediators of inflammation
that are formed from
arachidonic acid.
Arachidonic acid is a long-chain
inflammatory omega-6 fatty acid
found in animal fats.
The biggest contributors
are chicken and eggs,
which together contribute
nearly half of American intake.
That’s been suggested as an
explanation of why those eating
more plant-based appear to
have better mental health;
they’re not suffering the
“cascade of neuro-inflammation”
caused by arachidonic acid;
why removing eggs, chicken and other
meat was shown in a randomized
controlled trial to improve mood,
suggesting the arachidonic acid
might be negatively impacting mood
states and may help explain
the impact of more plant-based
diets on inflammatory diseases
like rheumatoid arthritis.
So, that may help explain why
maintaining a plant-based diet
appears to be necessary “after
the fast to prevent the recurrence
of symptoms and
inflammatory activity,”
or as one popular
press article put it,
fasting may just be a tool to
get you to radically kickstart
a change in the way you eat.
The strongest evidence of the benefits
of fasting surrounds the treatment
of an autoimmune joint disease
known as rheumatoid arthritis,
as I detailed in my last video.
There was a German study suggesting
benefits for osteoarthritis as well,
with reported improvements
in pain and joint function,
but we'd really need randomized
controlled trials to know for sure.
The researchers despair that
they only had 30 patients,
but that's 30 times more than
many reports on fasting
in the medical literature, which
may detail only single cases.
For example, a woman with
a rare autoimmune disease
known as mixed
connective-tissue disease,
which can cause all sorts of painful
and distressing symptoms,
treated with steroids in an attempt
to suppress her immune system.
But 21 days later, off her medications,
her symptoms improved with fasting,
and more importantly,
seemed to stay away.
So, does fasting work for
mixed connective-tissue disease?
Well, all we can say is, hey,
at least it worked at least once.
A similar success story was reported
with fibromyalgia: a woman with
pain throughout her body, couldn't
sustain activity, on lots of drugs,
but ended up symptom
free 24 days later,
and remained that way
at least a month later.
But when a modified fasting regimen
was tried on dozens of individuals,
the benefits seen at two weeks
largely disappeared by week 12.
What about lupus?
A 45-year-old woman remaining in pain
despite her immunosuppressive drugs,
but pain free by day four of fasting,
and remained symptom free
for a year, before wiping them
out again with a second fast.
Now, note this wasn't just fasting,
but fasting followed by a plant-based
diet in an attempt to solidify the gains.
And a strictly plant-based diet---
zero animal protein---alone
has been shown to control
symptoms in at least some cases.
The same with sacroiliitis, a common
manifestation of ankylosing spondylitis,
an autoimmune arthritis that
primarily affects the spine,
causing back pain that
can last for years.
They tried all sorts of conventional
therapies and drugs,
but the pain still didn't go away.
So, they tried recommending
the complete avoidance
of animal foods
and saw distinct persistent improvement
within days---until he ate meat again.
But back on plant-based nutrition,
he was off most of his drugs, almost
completely free of symptoms.
So at least in this case, inflammatory
pain refractory to other treatment
was abolished by eating healthier.
So, hey, at least it's worth a try.
Autoimmune glomerulonephritis,
where your body attacks
your own kidneys, is a
common manifestation of lupus.
In a case series of 29 patients
who were fasted for 60 hours
and then just put on fruits and
vegetables until they got better,
described such remarkable recoveries
that fasting, in their opinion,
should be an essential
part of treatment.
What about multiple sclerosis,
an autoimmune nerve disease?
Sufferers were randomized
to a fasting mimicking diet,
meaning a modified fast that started
out with an 800-calorie-a-day diet
of fruit, rice, or potatoes, and
then they spent a week sipping
a few hundred calories of
flaxseed oil and vegetable broth
before transitioning to a
plant-based Mediterranean diet.
And over the next three months,
experienced a significant improvement
in overall quality of life.
They also tried a ketogenic diet,
but that failed to offer clinically
or statistically significant
overall benefit.
And finally, chronic urticaria,
hives, where you get a rash
of itchy weals and welts,
started to improve
on day three of the fast and
completely disappeared by day 11.
This is consistent with studies out of
Germany and Japan that evidently showed
around a 75% effectiveness for
such patients with what looks like
some sort of tea with sugar diet.
It's certainly worth giving
fasting therapy a try,
but of course fasting should only be
done under trained medical supervision.
Otherwise you'd never know if you have
some hidden underlying kidney issue
that could land you in a coma
and then in the morgue.
You have to have your kidney function
and electrolytes monitored
to make sure your body
is up for the challenge.
Despite the potential benefits,
water-only fasting is not a cure or
treatment in the traditional sense.
It's simply intended to promote the
body's self-healing mechanisms,
since, by definition,
fasting is unsustainable.
In order to maintain the results
obtained by water-only fasting,
it is necessary to adhere to a health-
promoting lifestyle that includes
a healthy diet of minimally processed
plant foods, sleep, and exercise.